Vermont Connecticut Royster Papers
Vermont Connecticut Royster Papers
1931-1971
Royster, Vermont, 1914-
14.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, former editor of the Wall Street Journal. Correspondence and invitations (1931-1971); subject files; manuscriptdrafts and typescript for A Pride of Prejudices; articles, newpaper columns (1964-1971), and editorials (1948-1970); speeches (1959-1971); material relating to the American Society of Newpaper Editors; clippings, photographs, and press releases. Includes letters of Dwight D. Eisenhower, Barry Goldwater, Richard Nixon, and others.
149556
Biographical History
Vermont Connecticut Royster (1914-1996) was a Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and editor of The Wall Street Journal from 1958 to 1971.
Born in Raleigh, North Carolina, Vermont C. Royster graduated from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1935. In 1936 he was hired as a reporter by The Wall Street Journal, where a sixty-year career took him from staff reporter to Washington correspondent to the editor's chair (1958-1971). At the time of his death in 1996 he held the post of editor emeritus. He also commanded a U.S. Navy destroyer during World War II.
Among Royster's awards were two Pulitzer Prizes, the William Allen White Award, and the Presidential Medal of Freedom. He also served as president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Vermont Connecticut Royster Papers consist of two parts which have not been integrated.
Part I
Part I contains five series: correspondence; clubs, associations, and committees; writings; published material; and general files. Items of interest in this collection include several typewritten and signed letters by such persons as former U.S. President Dwight David Eisenhower, former U.S. Senator Barry Goldwater from Arizona, former U.S. Senator Robert F. Kennedy, and former U.S. President Richard M. Nixon.
Part II
Part II contains correspondence (primarily with readers of The Wall Street Journal), subject files, manuscripts, and published material. Published material contains items both by and about Royster, including some of his poetry.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence relating to invitations, speaking engagements, and other professional matters are arranged chronologically; the remaining correspondence is alphabetical by correspondent. Clubs, associations and committees are alphabetical by organization name. Writings and published material are subdivided by type and within that are arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
has the papers of numerous notable journalists; please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Goldwater, Barry, 1938-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Royster, Vermont, 1914-; American Society of Newspaper Editors.; Wall Street journal.; Journalists -- United States.; Journalism -- United States.; Journalism, Commercial -- United States.; Newspaper editors -- United States.; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc.; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc. -- Editorials.; United States -- Politics and government, 1945-1989.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vermont C. Royster, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence (Part I)
  - General
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1962-1965, 17 folders (Box 1)
    - 1965-1967, 15 folders (Box 2)
    - 1968-1969, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Invitations and meetings, 1961-1971; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Speaking engagements, 1962-1967; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Speaking engagements and trips, 1962-1971; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Speaking invitations, declined, 1968-1971; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - "Thinking Things Over"
    - 1964-1969, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Papal Encyclical (Box 5)
  - Trips
    - European (Box 5)
    - Far East (Box 5)
    - India (Box 5)
    - Middle East (Box 5)
    - Russia
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Reports and articles (Box 5)
      - Testimony (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Advice, requests for (Box 5)
  - Articles, outside
    - Declined (Box 5)
    - Published (Box 5)
  - Biography, Sawney Web (Box 5)
  - Business
    - Conferences (Box 5)
    - Ventures (Box 5)
  - CED (Committee for Economic Development) (Box 5)
  - Chapel Hill appointment (Box 5)
  - Comments and questionnaires (Box 5)
  - Companies (Box 6)
  - Congratulatory letters, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Dateline Magazine (Box 6)
  - De Gaulle, General of France (Box 6)
  - Director and Senior Vice President, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Dow Jones averages (Box 6)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower (Box 6)
  - Barry Goldwater (Box 6)
  - Government personnel (Box 6)
  - Individuals, includes 1 letter, Robert F. Kennedy (Box 6)
  - Lyndon Johnson (Box 6)
  - John F. Kennedy, includes 1 letter, Robert F. Kennedy (Box 6)
  - Richard M. Nixon, 17 letters, 1 photocopy (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Law Review (Box 6)
  - Presidency of ASNE (American Society of Newspaper Editors) (Box 6)
  - Recommendations and endorsements (Box 6)
  - Reprints (Box 6)
  - Retirement, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Romney, George (Box 6)
  - Governor Scranton (Box 6)
  - Television radio appearances (Box 6)
- Clubs, associations, and committees (Part I)
  - ASNE (American Society of Newspaper Editors)
    - Backstop program (Box 6)
    - The Bulletin (Box 6)
    - Canadian officials (Box 6)
    - Committees
      - Appointments (Box 6)
      - Bulletin Advisory (Box 6)
      - Editorial Future (Box 6)
      - Education For Journalism (Box 6)
      - Ethics (Box 6)
      - Freedom of Information (Box 6)
      - International Communication (Box 6)
      - Membership (Box 6)
      - Nominations (Box 6)
      - Press and Bar, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Program (Box 6)
    - Convention references (Box 6)
    - Correspondence
      - Canadian (Box 6)
      - General (Box 7)
      - Presidents (Box 7)
    - DSM Dues (Box 7)
    - Guests (Box 7)
    - Hall Party (Box 7)
    - Hilton Hotel (Box 7)
    - Judges (Box 7)
    - Lists of Canadian newspapermen (Box 7)
    - Meetings
      - Banquet (Box 7)
      - Fall Board (Box 7)
      - Montreal Board (Box 7)
      - Queen Elizabeth (Box 7)
      - Reception
        - Sunday (Box 7)
        - Monday (Box 7)
        - Tuesday, 4 folders (Box 7)
        - Wednesday, 4 folders (Box 7)
        - Thursday, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Newspapers, lists of Canadian (Box 7)
    - Social activities (Box 7)
    - Speakers (non-participating) (Box 7)
    - Staff memos (Box 7)
    - Trips (Box 7)
    - Working Program (Box 7)
  - DECO (Destroyer Escort Commanding Officers of World War II) (Box 7)
  - Economic Club (Box 7)
  - International Press Institute (Box 7)
  - National Conference of Editorial Writers (Box 7)
  - North Carolina Society (Box 7)
  - Overseas Press Club (Box 7)
  - University of North Carolina Alumni Association, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Recess Club (Box 7)
  - Sigma Delta Chi (Box 7)
  - Silurian Society (Box 7)
  - University Club (Box 7)
  - Webb School (Box 7)
- Writings (Part I)
  - Books
    - A Pride of Prejudices, 1949
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Rough Draft, 12 folders (Box 8)
      - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Journey Through the Soviet Union, galley (Box 8)
  - Articles and news stories (Box 8)
  - Articles offered, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Columns
    - "Thinking Things Over", 1964-1971; 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Editorials, clippings of
    - 1948-1950 (Box 8)
    - 1951-1970, 13 folders (Box 9)
  - Speeches and speaking engagements
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - 1959, 1962-1971, 20 folders (Box 9)
  - Story suggestions, 1968; 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Reprints of articles and speeches, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Letters to the editor, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Complaints, news and editorial, 1967-1970; 2 folders (Box 10)
- Published material (Part I)
  - Articles
    - "Provocative Premiere" (Box 10)
    - "Eggheads in Action" (Box 10)
    - "The Epermanis Story" (Box 10)
    - "'Prosperity' Paradox Along Route 40" (Box 10)
    - "Self Portrait of a Man Who Happened to be President" (Box 10)
    - "Sherman Adams: The Sad Part of the Story" (Box 10)
    - "Taft Phenomenon" (Box 10)
    - "Adlai E. Stevenson" (Box 10)
    - "Law and Men" in The World of the Wall Street Journal (Introduction) (Box 10)
    - "Billie Sol and the Sugar" (Box 10)
    - "A Lesson in Vigilance" (Box 10)
    - "How to Pick a Pocket or Two" (Box 10)
    - "Inflation and Business" (Box 10)
    - "Price of Indulgence" (Box 10)
    - "The Public Be Damned" (Box 10)
    - "Chronic Distress" (Box 10)
    - "Russia's People" (Box 10)
    - "Hiding a Railroad Wreck" (Box 10)
    - "Dilemma of the Airwaves" (Box 10)
    - "Pawns and Gambits in a Long Game" (Box 10)
    - "A Lesson from the U-2" (Box 10)
    - "The Just and the Unjust" (Box 10)
    - "The Moral Issue in Mississippi" (Box 10)
    - "Some Thoughts on American Business" (Box 10)
    - "The Dream and the Reality" (Box 10)
    - "A Tale of Our Times" (Box 10)
    - "Some Shop Talk About a Strike" (Box 10)
    - "A Sense of Purpose" in The New World of The Wall Street Journal (Box 10)
  - Speeches
    - "The Future of The Newspaper--The Darwinian Theory of Journalism" in Greater Communications Effectiveness (Box 10)
- General files (Part I)
  - Clippings, 1950-1968; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Photos (Box 11)
  - Plaque (Box 11)
  - Press releases (Box 11)
  - Printed material (Box 11)
  - Writings by others (Box 11)
- Correspondence (Part II)
  - Personal, incoming, B-T (Box 12)
  - re: Articles submitted (Wall Street Journal), 1961-1963 (Box 12)
  - re: Books, 1962-1963 (Box 12)
  - re: Criticisms and complaints (Wall Street Journal), 1962 (Box 12)
  - Invitations, 1961-1963 (Box 12)
  - re: Letters to the Editor (Wall Street Journal), 1962-1963; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - re: Pulitzer Prize with dictated replies, 1953; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Readers of the Wall Street Journal
    - November 1962-September 1963 (Box 14)
    - October 1963-December 1963, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - March 1964 (Box 15)
  - re: Reprints, 1963-1964 (Box 15)
  - re: USSR trip, 1963-1964 (Box 15)
- Subject files (Part II)
  - Awards and certificates (Box 16)
  - Far Eastern trip, 1959 (Box 16)
  - Headlines: declaration of war, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Notes (Box 16)
  - Photographs (Box 16)
  - Press releases (Box 16)
  - Programs and meetings (Box 16)
  - Pulitzer Prize material, 1949; 1951; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Radio program, "The American Forum" (Box 16)
  - Wall Street Journal (Box 16)
- Manuscripts (Part II)
  - Articles (Box 16)
  - Essays, University of North Carolina period, 1931 (Box 16)
  - Journals, Russian Journey no. 1, 2, 1962 (Box 16)
  - Interviews, Khrushchev, 13 Jul 1962 (Box 17)
  - Plays, University of North Carolina period, 1931-1935 (Box 17)
  - Short stories, University of North Carolina period, 1931-1935 (Box 17)
- Published material (Part II)
  - Articles
    - About Royster (Box 17)
    - By Royster (Box 17)
  - Books
    - In Hoc Anno Domini / Royster (Box 17)
    - Journey Through the Soviet Union / Royster (Box 17)
  - Magazine, The Masthead, edited by Royster (Box 17)
  - Clippings
    - About Royster (Box 17)
    - By Royster (Box 17)
  - Poems (Box 17)
  - Speeches (Box 17)